<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="aslak.nospam@users.sf.net">Aslak Hellesoy</author>
        <title>Branches and Tags</title>
    </properties>

    <head>
        <link rel="shortcut icon" href="../favicon.ico" />
        <link rel="icon" href="../favicon.ico" />
    </head>

    <body>
        <section name="Branches and Tags">
            <p>
                The branches are a feature of CVS that allows the development to be partitioned
                so that one stream does not affect the other. They prove to be useful, when
                there is a need to perform modifications that are hard to perform as a
                consecutive gradual transitions that work well in the usual course of
                development. When files that are depended upon by numerous other files need to
                be substantially changed all the other would have to be modified along with
                them. That would require that a lone developer performs all these changes in his
                own snapshot and then checks them all in, causing the sources to leap forward.
                As your project grows, situations arise that this is no longer possible. It's good to
                have version control on the gradual changes as opposed to quantum-leap changes.
                It's also important to have the larges set of eyes possible looking at the code
                as soon as possible. On the other hand, we strive to keep XDoclet CVS tree
                compilable and working at all times. This calls for usage of branches whenever
                vast modifications of the sources are needed.
            </p>
            <p>
                The
                <a href="http://www.red-bean.com/cvsbook/">CVS book</a> describes multiple
                approaches to performing development using branches. The simplest approach
                called
                <em>Flying Fish technique</em> will fit our needs best.
                It involves creating a branch when there is a need for a separate thread of
                development, and abandoning the branch once all the changes are merged with the
                trunk.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Branches">
                <p>
                    XDoclet CVS has following branches:
                </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Branch Name</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                        <th>Date Branched</th>
                        <th>Status</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <code>MODULE_REFACTORING_BRANCH</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>Module refactoring branch</td>
                        <td>05/2002</td>
                        <td>CLOSED</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <code>XDOCLET_MAVEN</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>Maven integration branch</td>
                        <td>07/2002</td>
                        <td>CLOSED</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Tags">
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Tag Name</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                        <th>Date Tagged</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <code>XDoclet-v1-2beta1</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>XDoclet 1.2 Beta 1 Tag</td>
                        <td>02/10/2002</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <code>XDoclet-v1-2beta2</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>XDoclet 1.2 Beta 2 Tag (includes some small fixes not included in the distribution)</td>
                        <td>06/01/2003</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <code>XDoclet-v1-2beta3</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>XDoclet 1.2 Beta 3 Tag (includes some small fixes not included in the distribution)</td>
                        <td>17/06/2003</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <code>XDoclet-v1-2</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>XDoclet 1.2 Final Release tag</td>
                        <td>24/11/2003</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
