<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Developer Guide</title>
	</properties>

    <head>
        <link rel="shortcut icon" href="../favicon.ico" />
        <link rel="icon" href="../favicon.ico" />
    </head>

	<body>
		<section name="Developer Guide">
		    <subsection name="New XDoclet Developer? Welcome!">
		    	<p>
		    		There are a variety of ways to participate. Regardless of how you choose to
		    		participate, we suggest you to <a href="../mail-lists.html">join the mailing list</a>
		    		first.
				</p>
				<p>
					Feel the irresistible urge to write quality code? Then <a href="../mail-lists.html">join</a> the XDoclet
					<a href="../team-list.html">project team</a> today (send an email to the xdoclet-devel mailing list)!
				</p>
			</subsection>
            <subsection name="Coding Conventions">
                <p>
                    Below is a list of coding conventions that are specific to XDoclet, everything
                    else not specifically mentioned here should follow the official
                    <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/html/CodeConvTOC.doc.html">Sun Java Coding Conventions</a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    1. Brackets that begin and end classes and methods should begin and end on a new line and should exist even for one line statements.
                </p>
                <p>
                    2. 4 space indent. <b>NO tabs</b>. Period. We understand that many developers like to use tabs, but
                    the fact of the matter is that in a distributed development environment where diffs are sent to the
                    mailing lists by both developers and the version control system (which sends commit log messages),
                    the use tabs makes it impossible to preserve legibility.
                </p>
                <p>
                    3. JavaDoc <b>MUST</b> exist on all methods. If your code modifications use an existing
                    class/method/variable which lacks JavaDoc, it is required that you add it. This will improve the
                    project as a whole.
                </p>
                <p>
                    4. If you contribute to a file (code or documentation), add yourself to the authors list at the top
                    of the file. Your sourceforge email address is preferred. Do not include the @ sign, as email spiders
                    will put your email in spam lists. For java files the preferred Javadoc format is:
                </p>
                <source>@author &lt;a href="mailto:user at domain.com"&gt;John Doe&lt;/a&gt;</source>
                <p>
                    Thanks for your cooperation.
                </p>
            </subsection>
			<subsection name="Further Reading">
				<ul>
                    <li><a href="architecture.html">Architecture</a></li>
                    <li><a href="branches.html">Branches and Tags</a></li>
					<li><a href="planning.html">Planning</a></li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
